National Association for Public School Adult Education (NAPSAE) Records
National Association for Public School Adult Education (NAPSAE) Records
1934-1964
National Association for Public School Adult Education
3.0 linear ft.
Correspondence, printed material, reports, budgets, minutes, newsletters, and clippings relating to States Projects Committee, workshops, and other affiliates of the National Education Association of the United States. Includes material pertaining to the American Association of School Administrators, the American Labor Education Service, Robert A. Luke, Elmer A. Mueller, and the National Education Association.
149350
Biographical History
The National Association for Public School Adult Education (NAPSAE) was founded in 1952 to provide leadership for the development of adult education in the public schools. Specifically, the organization assisted local adult education di-rectors in developing and improving their programs, and encouraged interest in liberal adult education of superintendents, school boards, and the public. Its work was handled by the State Projects Committee, headed by an Executive Secretary.
NAPSAE was a department of the National Education Association (NEA) and was affiliated with World Confederation of Organizations of the Teaching Profession. Funds were also provided by the Fund for Adult Education and the Department of Health, Education, and Welfare.
Membership in the organization was on an active or associate basis. Services varied from consultation with administrators to grants and workshops for establishing, expanding, and improving adult education programs. NAPSAE publications include the journals Swap Shop for Administrators, published six times yearly; Techniques for Teachers of Adults and Pulse of Public School Adult Education, each published eight times yearly; and the annual Public School Adult Educator's Almanac, as well as a variety of handbooks, slides, films, posters, and folders.
NAPSAE has since changed its name to the National Association for Public & Continuing Adult Education (NAPCAE).
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The National Association for Public School Adult Education (NAPSAE) Records are divided into three sections: State Projects, Workshops, and Other National Education Association (NEA) Affiliates. The collection includes correspondence, printed material such as newspaper and magazine clippings, newsletters, reports, programs, budgets, pamphlets, minutes, and questionnaires. The collection includes material pertaining to the American Association of School Administrators, the American Labor Education Service, Robert A. Luke, Elmer A. Mueller, and the National Education Association.
The States Projects section is divided into subsections of State Projects Committee and States. Material dealing with the State Projects Committee includes applications for grants, minutes of committee meetings, reports on state visits, as well as correspondence. The tentative format of the Project Cities Casebook, containing case studies of NAPSAE-grant districts, is also in this section. The States subsection includes material dealing with particular adult education programs and plans in various states and project cities. Most of the material is correspondence, but local workshop programs, district studies (notably in Utah and Oklahoma), and newspaper and magazine clippings are also filed here.
The Workshops section contains four folders of material concerning Project Directors' workshops and the two-week Community Leadership Laboratory. Tentative and final programs, correspondence, pamphlets, memoranda, and reports are included.
The section of projects by Other NEA affiliates includes materials dealing with two educational organizations, the American Association of School Administrators (AASA) and the American Labor Education Service (ALES). The AASA materials concern a 1962 study of numerous foundations and their aid to elementary and secondary public schools and to individual administrators. Correspondence in this section is arranged alphabetically. A comprehensive report is also included.
Most of the ALES material is printed material, either publications or mimeographed or dittoed programs on workshops. Publications include the annual reports; bulletins; Focus on the United Nations; a report of the international affairs pro-gram; a report on New Jersey minority program; and reports on international education and labor exchange. The workshops section contains a variety of pamphlets and programs on annual labor education workshops supported or sponsored by the ALES.
Arrangement of the Collection
The material is divided into three series: State Projects, Workshops, and other National Education Association (NEA) Affiliates. Within these sections, folders are alphabetically arranged. Correspondence is found in all sections, and in the first two it is chronologically arranged. Incoming letters are attached ahead of outgoing letters.
Related Material
The library holds a considerable number of collections related to adult and continuing education. Please refer to for a complete listing of all adult education collections.
In particular, see the records of the successor organization,
National Association for Public Continuing & Adult Education (NAPCAE)
. Also, large numbers of NAPSAE's newsletters Swap Shop for Administrators, Techniques for Teachers of Adults, and Pulse of Public School Adult Education may be found in the William Langner Papers.
Subject and Genre Headings
Adult education; Luke, Robert A.; Mueller, Elmer A.; American Association of School Administrators; American Labor Education Service; National Association for Public Continuing & Adult Education -- Archives; National Association for Public School Adult Education -- Archives; National Education Association of the United States.; Adult education -- United States.; Evening and continuation schools -- United States.; Correspondence.; Minutes (administrative records); Newsletters.; Questionnaires.; Reports.; Adult education teachers.; Educators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the National Association for Public School Adult Education, 1968.
Inventory
- State projects
  - State Projects Committee
    - Applications for grants
      - Applications, 1957-1964 (Box 1)
      - Rejections, 1960-1963 (Box 1)
      - Withdrawals, 1961-1963 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1958-1963; 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Minutes, 1954-1963 (Box 1)
    - Projects Cities casebook, 1963 (Box 1)
    - Reports on state visits, 1954-1962 (Box 1)
  - States
    - Arkansas, 1961-1962 (Box 2)
    - California, 1963 (Box 2)
    - Colorado
      - Department of Education, 1954-1964 (Box 2)
      - Fort Collins, 1963 (Box 2)
    - Delaware, 1963-1964 (Box 2)
    - Florida, 1961-1964 (Box 2)
    - Georgia, 1957-1963 (Box 2)
    - Hawaii, 1961-1963 (Box 2)
    - Illinois, 1959-1963 (Box 2)
    - Iowa, 1958-1962 (Box 2)
    - Kansas, 1956-1962 (Box 2)
    - Kentucky, 1963-1964 (Box 2)
    - Maryland, 1961-1963 (Box 2)
    - Massachusetts, 1959-1963 (Box 2)
    - Michigan, 1958-1964 (Box 2)
    - Minnesota
      - Austin, 1959-1964 (Box 3)
      - Department of Education, 1954-1956; 1957-1963 (Box 3)
    - Mississippi, 1959-1960 (Box 3)
    - New Jersey, 1957-1959 (Box 3)
    - New York
      - Herkimer, 1961-1963 (Box 3)
      - Middletown, 1963-1964 (Box 3)
      - Poughkeepsie, 1961-1962 (Box 3)
    - Ohio
      - Canton, 1962-1963 (Box 3)
      - Department of Education, 1956-1960 (Box 3)
    - Oklahoma
      - Department of Education, 1955-1960 (Box 3)
      - McAlester, 1961-1963 (Box 3)
    - Pennsylvania, 1959-1962 (Box 3)
    - Rhode Island
      - Department of Education, 1959-1960 (Box 4)
      - Warren, 1961-1963 (Box 4)
    - South Carolina
      - Department of Education, 1959-1965 (Box 4)
      - Walhalla, 1962-1963 (Box 4)
    - Texas, 1961-1962 (Box 4)
    - Utah
      - Department of Public Instruction, 1957-1964 (Box 4)
      - Weber County, 1962-1963 (Box 4)
    - Washington, 1961-1963 (Box 4)
    - Wisconsin, 1961-1963 (Box 4)
- Workshops
  - Community Leadership Laboratory, 1963 (Box 4)
  - Project Directors' Workshop, 1962-1964 (Box 4)
- Other NEA affiliates
  - American Association of School Administrators (AASA), study of foundations' aid to education
    - Administrators' questionnaires, 1962 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1962 (Box 5)
    - Foundation questionnaires
      - Affirmative responses, 1962 (Box 5)
      - Negative responses, 1962; 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Report of Committee on Foundations, 1963 (Box 5)
  - American Labor Education Service (ALES)
    - Publications
      - Annual reports, 1934-1961; 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Bulletin, 1935-1960 (Box 6)
      - Focus on the United Nations, 1958-1960 (Box 6)
      - International labor education, 1950-1957 (Box 6)
      - Report of international affairs program, 1955-1960 (Box 6)
      - Report on New Jersey minority program, 1944-1948 (Box 6)
    - Workshops
      - Education in world affairs, 1952-1961 (Box 6)
      - Labor education workshops, 1937-1961 (Box 6)
      - School on United Nations, 1954-1961 (Box 6)
      - Washington's Birthday conference, 1938-1962 (Box 6)
      - White Collar workshops, 1935-1961 (Box 6)